When you come to TEDx, you always think about technology,
عندما نقول TEDx دائماً تتبادر لذهنك التكنولوجيا.
the world changing, becoming more innovative.
يتغير العالم، يصبح أكثر إبداعاً.
You think about the driverless.
تفكر في سيارة بدون سائق.
Everyone's talking about driverless cars these days,
هذه الأيام الجميع يتكلمون عن تلك السيارات،
and I love the concept of a driverless car,
وأنا أحب فكرة السيارة بدون سائق،
but when I go in one, you know,
لكن عندما أركب واحدة،
I want it really slow,
أريدها أن تسير ببطء شديد،
I want access to the steering wheel and the brake, just in case.
وأن أستطيع التحكم بعجلة القيادة والمكابح تحسباً لأي طارئ.
I don't know about you, but I am not ready for a driverless bus.
لا أعلم رأيكم ولكني لست مستعدّاً لركوب حافلة بدون سائق.
I am not ready for a driverless airplane.
لست مستعداً لركوب طائرة بدون طيار.
How about a driverless world?
ماذا عن عالم بلا قائد ؟
And I ask you that
و أنا أسألكم هذا السؤال
because we are increasingly in one.
لأننا بالفعل في عالم بلا قائد و بشكل متزايد.
It's not supposed to be that way.
ليس من المفترض أن يكون كذالك
We're number one,
فنحن في المقدمة،
the United States is large and in charge.
الولايات المتحدة بلد كبير و مسؤول.
Americanization and globalization for the last several generations
في نظر الأجيال الحديثة، الأمركة والعولمة
have basically been the same thing.
هما شيء واحد.
or it's the IMF, the World Bank,
صندوق النقد الدولي، البنك الدولي،
the Bretton Woods Accord on currency,
إتفاق (بريتون وودز) حول العملة
these were American institutions,
كل هذه مؤسسات أمريكية
our values, our friends, our allies, our money, our standards.
قيمنا، أصدقاؤنا، حلفاؤنا، أموالنا، معاييرنا.
That was the way the world worked.
هكذا كان يسير العالم.
So it's sort of interesting, if you want to look at how the US looks,
من المثير للاهتمام أن تروا -إذا أردتم- كيف تبدو الولايات المتحدة,
here it is.
ها هي ذا.
This is our view of how the world is run.
هذه هي رؤيتنا عن طريقة سير العالم.
President Obama has got the red carpet,
الرئيس (أوباما) على السجادة الحمراء
he goes down Air Force One,
ينزل من طائرته الرئاسية،
and it feels pretty good, it feels pretty comfortable.
و يبدو أن كل شيء على ما يرام و مريح.
Well, I don't know how many of you saw the China trip last week
لا أعلم كم منكم شاهد رحلة الصين الأسبوع الماضي
and the G20.
و مجموعة العشرين.
Oh my God. Right?
رباه! أليس كذلك؟
This is how we landed
هكذا هبطنا
for the most important meeting of the world's leaders in China.
متجهين لأهم اجتماع لقادة العالم في الصين.
The National Security Advisor was actually spewing expletives
وكان مستشار الأمن القومي يُطلق الشتائم
on the tarmac --
على الأسفلت،
no red carpet,
لم تكن هناك سجادة حمراء،
kind of left out the bottom of the plane
يبدو أنهم غادروا من مؤخرة الطائرة،
along with all the media and everybody else.
مع الصحافة والآخرين.
Later on in the G20,
لاحقاً في قمة العشرين،
well, there's Obama.
حسناً، ها هو (أوباما).
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Hi, George.
مرحباً، جورج.
Hi, Norman.
مرحباً، نورمان.
They look like they're about to get into a cage match, right?
يبدو أنهم على وشك الدخول في مباراة بالقفص، صحيح ؟
And they did. It was 90 minutes long, and they talked about Syria.
و قد حدث بالفعل لمدة 90 دقيقة، تحدثوا عن سوريا.
That's what Putin wanted to talk about.
هذا ما أراد (بوتن) أن يتحدث عنه.
He's increasingly calling the shots.
كان يمتلك زمام الأمور بشكل متزايد.
He's the one willing to do stuff there.
ويريد أن يقوم بأشياء هناك.
There's not a lot of mutual like or trust,
ليس هناك الكثير من الإعجاب أو الثقة المتبادلة،
but it's not as if the Americans are telling him what to do.
لكن ليس الأمريكان مَن يملون عليه ماذا يفعل
Uh-oh.
أوه
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
Xi Jinping seems fine.
(زي-جينبينج) يبدو بخير
Angela Merkel has -- she always does --
(أنجيلا ميركل) كعادتها
that look, she always does that.
لديها تلك النظرة.
But Putin is telling Turkish president Erdogan what to do,
لكن (بوتن) يخبر (أردوغان) ماذا عليه أن يفعل
and Obama is like, what's going on over there?
أما (أوباما) فلسان حاله، ماذا يحدث هناك ؟
You see. And the problem is it's not a G20,
حسنا ؟ والمشكلة أن تلك ليست قمة العشرين،
the problem is
المشكلة
it's a G-Zero world that we live in,
أنه عالم بلا كبار نعيش فيه
a world order where there is no single country or alliance
نظام عالمي ليس به أي دولة أو حليف
that can meet the challenges of global leadership.
قادر على مواجة تحديات تولّي قيادة العالم.
The G20 doesn't work,
قمة العشرين لا تنفع،
the G7, all of our friends, that's history.
و حقيقة أن السبعة الكبار كلهم أصدقاؤنا أصبحت من الماضي.
So globalization is continuing.
العولمة مستمرّة.
Goods and services and people and capital are moving across borders
تنتقل السلع والخدمات والبشر و رؤوس الأموال عبر الحدود
faster and faster than ever before,
أسرع من ذي قبل،
but Americanization is not.
أما الأمركة فلا.
So if I've convinced you of that,
إذا أقنعتكم بذلك،
I want to do two things with the rest of this talk.
أريد أن أقوم بشيئين في بقية المحادثة.
I want to talk about the implications of that
أريد أن أتحدث عن آثار ذلك
for the whole world.
على العالم أجمع.
I'll go around it.
سأمرّ على جميع الدول.
And then I want to talk about
بعدها، أريد أن أتحدث عن
what we think right here
ما نعتقده هنا
in the United States and in New York.
في الولايات المتحدة و نيويورك.
So why? What are the implications. Why are we here?
لماذا؟ ما هي الآثار، لماذا نحن هنا ؟
Well, we're here
حسناً، نحن هنا
because the United States,
لأنّ الولايات المتحدة،
we spent two trillion dollars on wars in Iraq and Afghanistan
أنفقت 2 تريليون دولار على الحروب في العراق و أفغانستان
that were failed.
و فشلت.
We don't want to do that anymore.
لا نريد القيام بذلك بعد الآن.
We have large numbers of middle and working classes
لدنيا أعداد كبيرة في الطبقة الوسطى و العاملة
that feel like they've not benefited from promises of globalization,
تشعر أنها لم تستفد من وعود العولمة
so they don't want to see it particularly.
فهم لا يريدونها بالذات.
And we have an energy revolution
كما لدينا الآن ثورة في مجال الطاقة
where we don't need OPEC or the Middle East the way we used to.
بالتالي لسا بحاجة للأوبيك أو الشرق الأوسط كما كنا سابقاً
We produce all that right here in the United States.
فنحن ننتج كل هذا هنا في الولايات المتحدة.
So the Americans don't want to be the global sheriff for security
ولذلك لا يرغب الأمريكان في أن يقوموا بدور شرطى العالم
or the architect of global trade.
أو مهندس التجارة العالمية.
The Americans don't want to even be the cheerleader of global values.
ولا حتى أن يكونوا المشجع الأول للقيم العالمية.
Well, then you look to Europe,
حسناً، لننظر إلى أوروبا،
and the most important alliance in the world
إلى أهم حليف لنا في العالم
has been the transatlantic relationship.
من بين حلفائنا عبر الأطلسي.
But it is now weaker than it has been at any point since World War II,
لكنها الآن في أضعف حالاتها منذ الحرب العالمية الثانية،
all of the crises, the Brexit conversations,
الأزمات، مباحثات انفصال بريطانيا،
the hedging going on between the French and the Russians,
التحوّط الدائر بين الفرنسيين والروس،
or the Germans and the Turks, or the Brits and the Chinese.
الألمان و الأترك، البريطانيين و الصينيين.
China does want to do more leadership.
تريد الصين أن تتولّى دوراً قياديّاً أكبر.
They do, but only in the economic sphere,
لكن على الصعيد الاقتصادي فقط،
and they want their own values, standards, currency,
ويريدون فرض قيمهم ومعاييرهم وعملتهم،
in competition with that of the US.
في منافسة مع نظرائهم الأمريكيين.
The Russians want to do more leadership.
الروس يريدون تولّي دور قيادي أكبر.
You see that in Ukraine,
ترون ذلك في أوكرانيا،
in the Baltic states, in the Middle East,
في دول البلطيق، في الشرق الأوسط،
but not with the Americans.
لكن ليس بالشراكة مع الأمريكان.
They want their own preferences and order.
فهم يريدون فرض أولوياتهم ونظامهم الخاص.
That's why we are where we are.
ولهذا فإننا على ما نحن عليه الآن.
So what happens going forward?
إذاً ماذا سيحدث لاحقاً ؟
Let's start easy,
فلنبدأ على مهل،
with the Middle East.
بالشرق الأوسط
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know, I left a little out,
تعلمون، لقد أسقطت بعض التفاصيل
but you get the general idea.
لكنكم فهمتم الفكرة العامّة.
Look, there are three reasons
هناك ثلاثة أسباب
why the Middle East has had stability such as it is. Right?
جعلت الشرق الأوسط ثابتاً على وضعه
One is because there was a willingness to provide
الأول، وجود رغبة في توفير
some level of military security by the US and allies.
مستوى معين من الأمن العسكري من قِبَل الولايات المتحدة و حلفائها.
Number two, it was easy to take a lot of cheap money out of the ground
الثاني، سهولة الحصول على الكثير من الأموال من الأرض
because oil was expensive.
لأن البترول غالي الثمن.
And number three
والثالث،
was no matter how bad the leaders were, the populations were relatively quiescent.
هدوء الشعب النسبي، مهما كان الحكام سيئون
They didn't have the ability, and many didn't have the will
فلم توجد القدرة أو الإرادة لدى الكثير منهم
to really rise up against.
للانتفاض ضد الحكّام.
Well, I can tell you, in a G-Zero world,
حسناً، يمكنني أن أقول لكم أنّه في عالم بلا كبار،
all three of those things are increasingly not true,
جميع تلك الأسباب تتلاشى مع الوقت،
and so failed states,
و هكذا تنهار الدول،
terrorism, refugees and the rest.
ويحدث الإرهاب، اللاجئين وغيرها.
Does the entire Middle East fall apart?
هل سيتفكك الشرق الأوسط بالكامل ؟
No, the Kurds will do better, and Iraq, Israel, Iran over time.
لا، فسيُبلي الأكراد بلاءً أفضل، بالإضافة للعراق وإسرائيل و إيران.
But generally speaking, it's not a good look.
لكن بشكل عام، لا تبدو الأمور على ما يرام.
OK, how about this guy?
حسناً، ماذا عن هذا الرجل؟
He's playing a poor hand very well.
إنّه يلعب دور المتسوّل بشكل جيد.
There's no question he's hitting above his weight.
ولا جدال في أنّ تأثيره يفوق حجمه الفعلي
But long term -- I didn't mean that.
لكن على المدى الطويل - أنا لم أقصد هذا
But long term, long term,
لكن على المدى الطويل، على المدى الطويل،
if you think that the Russians
إذا كنتَ تظن أن الروس مهدَّدين
were antagonized by the US and Europe expanding NATO right up to their borders
من توسيع أوروبا وأمريكا لمناطق حلف شمال الأطلسي قرب حدودهم
when we said they weren't going to,
عندما قلنا أنهما لن يقوما بذلك،
and the EU encroaching them,
بالإضافة لزحف الاتحاد الأوروبى تجاه روسيا،
just wait until the Chinese put hundreds of billions of dollars
فانتظر حتى يضخ الصينيون مئات المليارات من الدولارات
in every country around Russia they thought they had influence in.
في كل دولة حول روسيا يعتقد الروس أنهم يأثرون عليها.
The Chinese are going to dominate it. The Russians are picking up the crumbs.
سوف تسيطر الصين عليهم، وستجمع روسيا الفتات.
In a G-Zero world, this is going to be a very tense 10 years for Mr. Putin.
فى عالم بلا قادة، تنتظر السيد (بوتن)، عشرة سنين عجاف.
It's not all bad. Right?
الأمور ليست بذلك السوء، صحيح؟
Asia actually looks a lot better.
آسيا تبدو بحال أفضل بالفعل.
There are real leaders across Asia,
فهناك قادة حقيقيون في آسيا.
they have a lot of political stability.
ولديهم قدر كبير من الاستقرار السياسي.
They're there for a while.
فهم موجودون منذ فترة.
Mr. Modi in India,
السيد (مودي) في الهند،
Mr. Abe, who is probably about to get a third term written in
و السيد (آب)، الذي سيحصل على فترة ثالثة على الأرجح
in the Liberal Democratic Party in Japan,
عن الحزب الليبرالي الديمقراطي في اليابان،
of course Xi Jinping who is consolidating enormous power,
و طبعاً السيد (زي-جينبينج) صاحب القوة الهائلة،
the most powerful leader in China
فهو القائد الأقوى بالصين
since Mao.
منذ وفاة (ماو).
Those are the three most important economies in Asia.
تلك هي الاقتصادات الثلاثة الكبرى في آسيا.
Now look, there are problems in Asia.
لكن هناك مشكلات في آسيا.
We see the sparring over the South China Sea.
فنرى المناوشات في بحر الصين الجنوبي.
We see that Kim Jong Un, just in the last couple of days,
و نرى (كيم جونج أون) في الأيام القليلة الماضية
tested yet another nuclear weapon.
يجرّب سلاحاً نوويّاً جديداً.
But the leaders in Asia do not feel the need
إلا أن قادة آسيا لا يرون أن عليهم
to wave the flag,
حماية أحد،
to go xenophobic,
أو أن يعادوا الأجانب،
to actually allow escalation
أو أن يسمحوا بتصاعد
of the geopolitical and cross-border tensions.
توتّرات جيوسياسية أو عابرة للحدود.
They want to focus on long-term economic stability and growth.
فهم يريدون التركيزعلى الاستقرار والنمو الاقتصادي بعيد المدى.
And that's what they're actually doing.
و هذا ما يقومون به بالفعل.
Let's turn to Europe.
فلنعد الآن إلى أوروبا.
Europe does look a little scared in this environment.
تبدو أوروبا خائفة قليلاً في هذه البيئة.
So much of what is happening in the Middle East
خائفة مما يحدث في الشرق الأوسط
is washing up quite literally onto European shores.
والذي يتوافد حرفياً إلى السواحل الأوروبية.
You see Brexit and you see the concerns of populism
أنتم ترون انفصال بريطانيا والمخاوف من انتشار الإشتراكية
across all of the European states.
في كل دول أوروبا.
Let me tell you that over the long term,
دعوني أخبركم أنه على المدى البعيد،
in a G-Zero world,
في عالم بلا كبار،
European expansion will be seen to have gone too far.
سنرى أن التمدد الأوروبي قد تطور كثيراً.
Europe went right up to Russia, went right down to the Middle East,
ستصل أوروبا للأعلى حتى روسيا ولأسفل حتى الشرق الأوسط،
and if the world were truly becoming more flat and more Americanized,
وإذا كان العالم فعلاً يصبح أكثر انفتاحاً وأكثر أمركة،
that would be less of a problem,
فستكون المشكلة أقل،
but in a G-Zero world, those countries nearest Russia
إلا أنّه في عالم بلا كبار، تلك البلاد الأقرب لروسيا
and nearest the Middle East
والأقرب للشرق الأوسط
actually have different economic capabilities,
لديها إمكانيات اقتصادية مختلفة،
different social stability
و استقرار اجتماعي مختلف،
and different political preferences and systems than core Europe.
وأولويات ونظم سياسية مختلفة عن قلب أوروبا.
So Europe was able to truly expand
فإذا كانت أوروبا قادرة على التمدد
under the G7,
تحت قيادة السبعة الكبار،
but under the G-Zero, Europe will get smaller.
فإنها في غياب الكبار، ستنكمش.
Core Europe around Germany and France and others
إنّ قلب أوروبا حول ألمانيا و فرنسا وغيرهما
will still work, be functional, stable, wealthy, integrated.
سيبقى فاعل ومستقر وثريّ ومتماسك.
But the periphery,
لكن دول الأطراف،
countries like Greece and Turkey and others,
كاليونان و تركيا وغيرهما،
will not look that good at all.
لن تكون بخير على الإطلاق.
Latin America, a lot of populism,
دول أمريكا اللاتينية، انتشار الاشتراكية،
made the economies not go so well.
جعل الاقتصاد ليس على ما يرام.
They had been more opposed to the United States for decades.
تلك الدول كانت الأكثر معارضة للولايات المتحدة لعقود.
Increasingly, they're coming back.
وها هي تعود بقوة الآن.
We see that in Argentina.
نرى ذلك في الأرجنتين.
We see it with the openness in Cuba.
و نرى انفتاحها على كوبا.
We will see it in Venezuela when Maduro falls.
و سنرى ذلك في فنزويلا عندما يسقط (مادورو).
We will see it in Brazil after the impeachment
و سنرى ذلك في البرازيل بعد المحاكمة
and when we finally see a new legitimate president elected there.
وانتخاب رئيس شرعي جديد هناك.
The only place you see that is moving in another direction
المكان الوحيد الذى نراه يتحرك في اتجاه آخر
is the unpopularity of Mexican president Peña Nieto.
هو عدم شعبية رئيس المكسيك (بينيا نيتو).
There you could actually see a slip away from the United States
هناك، لن يكون للولايات المتحدة أي نفوذ
over the coming years.
في السنوات القادمة.
The US election matters a lot on that one, too.
الانتخابات الأمريكية مهمة لهذا الأمر أيضاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Africa, right?
أفريقيا، أليس كذلك؟
A lot of people have said it's going to be Africa's decade, finally.
يقولون أنه سيكون عصر أفريقيا في النهاية.
In a G-Zero world, it is absolutely an amazing time
في عالم بلا كبار، فإنه توقيت رائع
for a few African countries,
لبعض الدول الإفريقية،
those governed well with a lot of urbanization,
تلك المُدارة جيداً و التي على درجة عالية من المدنية،
a lot of smart people, women really getting into the workforce,
لديها الكثير من المواطنين الأذكياء، ونساؤها جزء من القوة العاملة،
entrepreneurship taking off.
ريادة الأعمال ستنطلق من هناك.
But for most of the countries in Africa,
لكن بالنسبة لمعظم الدول الإفريقية،
it's going to be a lot more dicey:
سيكون الأمر محفوف بالمخاطر:
extreme climate conditions,
الظروف المناخية القاسية،
radicalism both from Islam and also Christianity,
التطرّف الإسلامي و المسيحي،
very poor governance,
السلطة ضعيفة النفوذ،
borders you can't defend, lots of forced migration.
الحدود التي لا يمكن حمايتها، التهجير القسري.
Those countries can fall off the map.
من الممكن أن تُمحى تلك الدول من على الخريطة.
So you're really going to see an extreme segregation going on
سنرى عملية عزل شديدة تفصل
between the winners and the losers across Africa.
بين الفائزين و الخاسرين في أفريقيا.
Finally, back to the United States.
أخيراً، وبالعودة إلى الولايات المتحدة.
What do I think about us?
ماذا أعتقد بشأننا؟
Because there are a lot of upset people,
فهناك الكثير من الناس السّاخطين،
not here at TEDx, I know,
ليس هنا في TEDx، أعلم،
but in the United States, my God,
إنما في الولايات المتحدة، يا إلهي،
after 15 months of campaigning, we should be upset.
15 شهراً من الحملات الانتخابية من الطبيعي أن نستاء
I understand that.
أتفهّم هذا.
But a lot of people are upset because they say, "Washington's broken,
الكثير من الناس مستاؤون ويقولون " لقد حُطّمت واشنطن،
we don't trust the establishment, we hate the media."
نحن لا نثق بالمؤسّسات، ونكره الإعلام".
Heck, even globalists like me are taking it on the chin.
حتى أمثالي من مناصري العولمة يقبلون ذلك على مضض.
Look, I do think we have to recognize,
أعتقد أنه علينا أن ندرك،
my fellow campers,
بالنسبة لرفقاء المعسكر،
that when you are being chased by the bear,
أنه عندما يطاردك الدب،
in the global context, you need not outrun the bear,
- في السباق العالمي - ليس عليك أن تسبق الدب
you need to only outrun your fellow campers.
بل عليك فقط أن تسبق رفقاء معسكرك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, I just told you
لقد أخبرتكم للتو
about our fellow campers.
من هم رفقاء المعسكر.
Right? And from that perspective,
أليس كذلك؟ ومن هذا المنطلق،
we look OK.
نحن بخير.
A lot of people in that context say,
يقول الكثير من الناس في هذا السياق،
"Let's go dollar. Let's go New York real estate.
"فلنتعامل بالدولار، فلنستثمر في سوق العقارات في نيويورك،
Let's send our kids to American universities."
فلنرسل أبناءنا لجامعات أمريكا".
You know, our neighbors are awesome:
جيراننا رائعون،
Canada, Mexico and two big bodies of water.
كندا، المكسيك، ومساحتين كبيرتين من المياه.
You know how much Turkey would love to have neighbors like that?
أتعلمون كم تحب تركيا أن يكون لديها جيران كهؤلاء؟
Those are awesome neighbors.
هؤلاء جيران رائعون.
Terrorism is a problem in the United States.
إن الإرهاب يمثل مشكلة في الولايات المتحدة.
God knows we know it here in New York.
يعلم الله أننا نجده هنا في نيويورك.
But it's a much bigger problem in Europe than the US.
لكن مشكلته أكبر فى أوروبا من الولايات المتحدة.
It's a much bigger problem in the Middle East
و مشكلته أكبر في الشرق الأوسط
than it is in Europe.
منها في أوروبا.
These are factors of large magnitude.
هذه العوامل لها أهميّتها.
We just accepted 10,000 Syrian refugees, and we're complaining bitterly about it.
لقد استقبلنا 10.000 لاجئ سوري، و نتذمر من ذلك.
You know why? Because they can't swim here.
أتعلمون لماذا؟ لأنهم لا يستطيعون السباحة إلى هنا.
Right? I mean, the Turks would love to have only 10,000 Syrian refugees.
صحيح؟ سيود الأتراك كثيراً لو كان لديهم 10.000 لاجئ سوري فقط.
The Jordanians, the Germans, the Brits. Right?
الأردنيون، الألمان، البريطانيون. أليس كذلك؟
That's not the situation.
ليس هذا هو الحال.
That's the reality of the United States.
هذه حقيقة الولايات المتحدة.
Now, that sounds pretty good.
الآن، يبدو هذا جيداً.
Here's the challenge.
إليكم التحدي.
In a G-Zero world, the way you lead
في عالم بلا كبار، الطريق إلى القيادة
is by example.
هو أن نكون مثالاً يحتذى.
If we know we don't want to be the global cop anymore,
إذا علمنا أننا لا نريد أن نكون شرطي العالم بعد الآن،
if we know we're not going to be the architect of global trade,
إذا علمنا أننا لن نكون مهندسي التجارة العالمية،
we're not going to be the cheerleader of global values,
لن نكون مشجّعين للقيم العالمية،
we're not going to do it the way we used to,
و لن نقوم بأي شيء على الطريقة التى اعتدناها،
the 21st century is changing,
لأن القرن 21 يتغير،
we need to lead by example -- be so compelling
نحتاج أن نكون مثالاً يحتذى، كي نفرض قوتنا
that all these other people are going to still say,
لدرجة أن الآخرين سيظلوا يرددون،
it's not just they're faster campers.
"ليس فقط لأنها أسرع،
Even when the bear is not chasing us, this is a good place to be.
فحتى لو لم يكن هناك دب يطاردنا، فأمريكا مكان آمن لنا،
We want to emulate them.
نريد أن نفعل مثلهم".
The election process this year is not proving a good option
العملية الانتخابية لهذا العام لم تعطِ خياراً جيداً
for leading by example.
لم تكن مثالاً يحتذى به.
Hillary Clinton says it's going to be like the '90s.
تقول (هيلاري كلينتون) أن الحال سيكون كالتسعينات.
We can still be that cheerleader on values.
يمكننا أن نظل من مشجّعي القيم.
the architect of global trade.
يمكننا أن نظل مهندسي التجارة العالمية.
We can still be the global sheriff.
يمكننا أن نظل كشرطي للعالم.
And Donald Trump wants to bring us back to the '30s.
ويريد (دونالد ترامب) أن يرجعنا إلى الثلاثينات.
He's saying, "Our way or the highway. You don't like it, lump it." Right?
يقول "طريقنا أو طريق اللاعودة، اتخذوه أو تقبلوا الهزيمة" صحيح ؟
Neither are recognizing a fundamental truth of the G-Zero,
و لا يدرك أي منهما حقيقة أن العالم أصبح بلا كبار،
which is that even though the US is not in decline,
و أن دور الولايات المتحدة فيه ينقص،
it is getting objectively harder
وسيصبح أصعب بكثير
for the Americans to impose their will,
بالنسبة للأمريكان أن يفرضوا إرادتهم،
even have great influence,
أو حتى يكون لديهم تأثير قوي،
on the global order.
على النظام العالمي.
Are we prepared to truly lead by example?
هل نحن فعلياً مستعدون للقيادة عن طريق ضرب المثل؟
What would we have to do to fix this
ماذا علينا أن نفعل لإصلاح ذلك ؟
after November,
بعد نوفمبر،
after the next president comes in?
بعدما يأتي الرئيس القادم؟
Well, either we have to have another crisis that forces us to respond.
إما سيكون علينا مواجهة كارثة أخرى تجبرنا على التحرك.
A depression would do that.
قد تكون كساد اقتصادي.
Another global financial crisis could do this.
و قد تكون كارثة مالية أخرى.
God forbid, another 9/11 could do that.
قد تكون 9/11 أخرى، لا قدر الله.
Or, absent crisis,
و إن لم تحدث كارثة ما،
we need to see that the hollowing out, the inequality, the challenges
علينا أن ندرك أنّ تراجع قطّاع الصّناعة، اللامساواة،
are themselves urgent enough
عاجلة بما يكفي
to force our leaders to change,
لإجبار قادتنا على التغيير.
and that we have those voices.
نحن لدينا الأصوات،
Through our cell phones, individually,
عبر هواتفنا المحمولة، كل واحد منا،
we have those voices to compel them to change.
لدينا تلك الأصوات التى تدفعهم للتغيير.
There is, of course, a third choice,
هناك طبعاً خيار ثالث،
perhaps the most likely one,
و هو الغالب،
which is that we do neither of those things,
أننا لن نقوم بأيّ من تلك الأشياء،
and in four years time you invite me back,
وخلال أربعة سنوات سوف تدعونني مرّة أخرى،
and I will give this speech yet again.
وسوف ألقي هذا الخطاب ثانيةً.
Thank you very, very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)